<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-18T21:56:18+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Agent of History</title><subtitle>A journey of exploration into the questions of how we broke and how we can heal.  A journey of exploration into the reintegration of Spirit and Matter.</subtitle><author><name>Joel Lazarus</name></author><entry><title type="html">Make Charity History</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/10/18/make-charity-history.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Make Charity History" /><published>2017-10-18T12:36:18+01:00</published><updated>2017-10-18T12:36:18+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/10/18/make-charity-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/10/18/make-charity-history.html">&lt;p&gt;There are many institutions in our culture and society that, for me, highlight the depth of our dysfunctionality and despair. Such institutions express the shocking degree to which a social system of artificially-created human misery has been so successfully naturalised that its universality and ubiquity has been rendered invisible. They also reveal how we are, wittingly or unwittingly, complicit in hiding truth, and how depressingly limited our collective imagination is. One such institution in the UK is the annual &lt;strong&gt;national do-something-silly-for-charity-shenanigan&lt;/strong&gt;. We have two primary charitythons like this: &lt;a href=&quot;http://r.search.yahoo.com/_ylt=A7x9UnJQYwNVP2YAYFZ3Bwx.;_ylu=X3oDMTBydWpobjZlBHNlYwNzcgRwb3MDMQRjb2xvA2lyMgR2dGlkAw--/RV=2/RE=1426314192/RO=10/RU=http://www.comicrelief.com//RK=0/RS=Gi8QdtN20YSCGRLGlweLcMiTRcg-&quot;&gt;Comic Relief&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://r.search.yahoo.com/_ylt=A7x9UnBhYwNVTVIAu3d3Bwx.;_ylu=X3oDMTByZWJ1c203BHNlYwNzcgRwb3MDMgRjb2xvA2lyMgR2dGlkAw--/RV=2/RE=1426314210/RO=10/RU=http://www.bbc.co.uk/pudsey//RK=0/RS=lyFK3uLBSLVRQZ48u7VOdR5V6Ws-&quot;&gt;Children in Need&lt;/a&gt;. On both these occasions, Brits come together to dress up, do silly things, bake cakes, etc in order to raise money for the poor and needy at home and abroad. The fact that every year the poor and needy are still with us and that their poverty and need grows is barely questioned and is used merely to justify a redoubling of efforts.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;JUSTIFY&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/comicreliefrednoseday2009presslaunchohgg7z2bplmx.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone  wp-image-166&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/comicreliefrednoseday2009presslaunchohgg7z2bplmx.jpg?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;Comic+Relief+Red+Nose+Day+2009+Press+Launch+Ohgg7z2BpLMx&quot; width=&quot;520&quot; height=&quot;391&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;JUSTIFY&quot;&gt;Comic Relief is one of the UK's largest overseas development charities. Its annual fund-raiser is called 'Red Nose Day' after the clown-inspired red noses that people all across the country wear. Alongside the money-raising fun and games of ordinary folk, the event is, inevitably, centred on celebrities and 'big-hearted' multi-national corporations. On Red Nose night, on TV, we are alternately entertained and then harrowed by comedians who travel among the world's poorest to capture both their suffering and, of course, the hope that Comic Relief and our money bring. Big corporations - this year it seems to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://rednoseday.pgtips.co.uk/&quot;&gt;PG Tips&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.persil.co.uk/red-nose-day/&quot;&gt;Persil &lt;/a&gt;(Unilever-owned tea and washing powder brands - get in on the act, showing us how humane and generous they are, by pledging big money in return for us buying their products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;JUSTIFY&quot;&gt;How can something so well-meaning, something that brings people together, something that has raised so many hundreds of millions of pounds for charity stir feelings of such anger and distress in me? I will answer this question by drawing on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/wilde-oscar/soul-man/&quot;&gt;work of Oscar Wilde&lt;/a&gt;, someone who understood precisely what charity constituted within capitalist society and who explained it with characteristic eloquence. For Wilde, it was quite 'inevitable' that people who found themselves 'surrounded by hideous poverty, by hideous ugliness, by hideous starvation' would be 'strongly moved by all this'. However, since, unfortunately, 'the emotions of man are stirred more quickly than man’s intelligence', 'with admirable, though misdirected intentions, they very seriously and very sentimentally set themselves to the task of remedying the evils that they see.&lt;strong&gt; But their remedies do not cure the disease: they merely prolong it. Indeed, their remedies are part of the disease&lt;/strong&gt;.' Thus, Wilde saw charity as an institution that 'degrades and demoralises' and 'creates a multitude of sins'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;JUSTIFY&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/oscar-wilde.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone  wp-image-167&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/oscar-wilde.jpg?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;oscar-wilde&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;364&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;JUSTIFY&quot;&gt;I stand with Oscar Wilde. &lt;strong&gt;Comic Relief constitutes merely the most degenerate expression of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Society_of_the_Spectacle&quot;&gt;spectacle&lt;/a&gt;-mediated, consumer-driven institution of contemporary charity.&lt;/strong&gt; I would suggest that not only does today's 'spectacle charity' serve as the eternal plaster over a gaping, festering social wound, it actually functions directly to sustain the system that injures us. First, spectacle charity does this by alleviating social pressure. Legitimate frustration and anger at blatant social injustice is channeled 'productively' into charitable activity. Second, spectacle charity serves to appease feelings of guilt among those who are, or at least feel, better off and luckier. It also tells those unlucky ones they should be grateful they're not far worse off in some Third World urban slum. Third, spectacle charity reinforces capitalist social relations by asking us to help alleviate suffering by acting as consumers – buying cakes, red noses, corporate sponsors' products. Fourth, spectacle charity serves to maintain the status quo by providing depoliticised depictions of human suffering. The political-economic root causes of, say, child poverty in the UK are not and cannot be confronted. Poverty is portrayed in technical terms as a mere lack of things: money, education, resources. Fifth, in this way, spectacle charity reinforces the status quo by reinforcing general thoughtlessness. 'Don't think, do!' is the general message here. In all these ways Comic Relief, and charity in general, does more harm than good by serving to maintain the status quo economically, socially, and culturally. I shall offer some evidence for these claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;JUSTIFY&quot;&gt;Yesterday, I tried to find out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/?gfe_rd=cr&amp;amp;ei=hmMDVYHGN4Xj8weY0oGoCw&amp;amp;gws_rd=ssl#q=where+are+comic+relief+red+noses+manufactured&quot;&gt;where Comic Relief's red noses were manufactured&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/?gfe_rd=cr&amp;amp;ei=hmMDVYHGN4Xj8weY0oGoCw&amp;amp;gws_rd=ssl#q=What+are+comic+relief+red+noses+made+from&quot;&gt;what they were made from&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, I was able to find out very little. With regard to labour, all I could establish was that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.comicrelief.com/support-us/partners&quot;&gt;Comic Relief had signed up&lt;/a&gt;, alongside other major charities and companies, to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ethicaltrade.org/&quot;&gt;'Ethical Trading Initiative' (ETI)&lt;/a&gt; under which partner NGOs (non-government organisations) monitors the companies (presumably, predominantly in China) that manufacture their orders. I also found a mixed (albeit quite old) report on the ETI's effects by Sussex University, found out that several major companies, including &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cafod.org.uk/News/UK-News/Boots-leaves-ETI&quot;&gt;Boots&lt;/a&gt;, had subsequently left the ETI, and that Primark, the company whose Bangladeshi subcontractors were guilty of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2013_Savar_building_collapse&quot;&gt;Rana Plaza tragedy&lt;/a&gt; in which 1,129 people needlessly died, is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ethicaltrade.org/about-eti/our-members&quot;&gt;an ETI member&lt;/a&gt;. With regard to the environment, I could find nothing except for the fact that red noses can be recycled at various outlets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;JUSTIFY&quot;&gt;Whether the conditions in these factories had improved under ETI or not is, for me, secondary to the telling fact that I was not able to establish where Comic Relief's red noses were made. This tells us everything we need to know about the &lt;strong&gt;hidden, alienated nature of capitalist social relations and the institutions of commodified, spectacle charity within it&lt;/strong&gt;. Comic Relief, an organisation dedicated to alleviating poverty, is largely blind to and reliant on the structure of class exploitation that creates this poverty. Thus, even if conditions are somewhat better in red nose factories, they are still exploitative. Why? Because it is the human labour within these factories that generates the surplus value that allows Comic Relief to sell these things for a profit. If this was not the case, these red noses would simply be produced in the UK. In terms of the environment, I am none the wiser, but pessimistic, as to the ecological cost of mass-producing millions of plastic red noses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;JUSTIFY&quot;&gt;Over a century ago, Oscar Wilde was acutely aware of the perversity of charity: 'It is immoral to use private property in order to alleviate the horrible evils that result from the institution of private property.' His ultimate conclusion resounds to this day: &lt;strong&gt;'The proper aim is to try and reconstruct society on such a basis that poverty will be impossible.&lt;/strong&gt;' The only thing that gives me heart on days like Red Nose Day is that people undoubtedly care. But, no amount of silly tomfoolery or hard, cold cash will end poverty. Capitalism breeds it, capitalism needs it. The goal of socialists like me is to encourage well-meaning, big-hearted folk (i.e. most people) to go beyond doing and take some time to explore and think about the root causes of our bleak situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;JUSTIFY&quot;&gt;Ten years ago, the major charities in the UK came together under the banner of '&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.makepovertyhistory.org/takeaction/&quot;&gt;Make Poverty History&lt;/a&gt;'. Remember the white plastic wristbands? In the UK and beyond, poverty has increased in the past ten years.&lt;a class=&quot;sdfootnoteanc&quot; href=&quot;#sdfootnote1sym&quot; name=&quot;sdfootnote1anc&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Let us, instead, take an approach that is at once more radical and realistic. &lt;strong&gt;To make poverty history means to make charity history, and to make charity history we must make capitalism history.&lt;/strong&gt; If we don't, Oscar Wilde's words will continue to resonate yet another century from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;sdfootnote1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;sdfootnote&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;sdfootnotesym&quot; href=&quot;#sdfootnote1anc&quot; name=&quot;sdfootnote1sym&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2014/08/exposing-great-poverty-reductio-201481211590729809.html&quot;&gt;If we reject the disgracefully and artificially low levels of indicators set by the multilateral development organisations. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Joel Lazarus</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">There are many institutions in our culture and society that, for me, highlight the depth of our dysfunctionality and despair. Such institutions express the shocking degree to which a social system of artificially-created human misery has been so successfully naturalised that its universality and ubiquity has been rendered invisible. They also reveal how we are, wittingly or unwittingly, complicit in hiding truth, and how depressingly limited our collective imagination is. One such institution in the UK is the annual national do-something-silly-for-charity-shenanigan. We have two primary charitythons like this: Comic Relief and Children in Need. On both these occasions, Brits come together to dress up, do silly things, bake cakes, etc in order to raise money for the poor and needy at home and abroad. The fact that every year the poor and needy are still with us and that their poverty and need grows is barely questioned and is used merely to justify a redoubling of efforts.&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt; Comic Relief is one of the UK's largest overseas development charities. Its annual fund-raiser is called 'Red Nose Day' after the clown-inspired red noses that people all across the country wear. Alongside the money-raising fun and games of ordinary folk, the event is, inevitably, centred on celebrities and 'big-hearted' multi-national corporations. On Red Nose night, on TV, we are alternately entertained and then harrowed by comedians who travel among the world's poorest to capture both their suffering and, of course, the hope that Comic Relief and our money bring. Big corporations - this year it seems to be PG Tips and Persil (Unilever-owned tea and washing powder brands - get in on the act, showing us how humane and generous they are, by pledging big money in return for us buying their products. How can something so well-meaning, something that brings people together, something that has raised so many hundreds of millions of pounds for charity stir feelings of such anger and distress in me? I will answer this question by drawing on the work of Oscar Wilde, someone who understood precisely what charity constituted within capitalist society and who explained it with characteristic eloquence. For Wilde, it was quite 'inevitable' that people who found themselves 'surrounded by hideous poverty, by hideous ugliness, by hideous starvation' would be 'strongly moved by all this'. However, since, unfortunately, 'the emotions of man are stirred more quickly than man’s intelligence', 'with admirable, though misdirected intentions, they very seriously and very sentimentally set themselves to the task of remedying the evils that they see. But their remedies do not cure the disease: they merely prolong it. Indeed, their remedies are part of the disease.' Thus, Wilde saw charity as an institution that 'degrades and demoralises' and 'creates a multitude of sins'. I stand with Oscar Wilde. Comic Relief constitutes merely the most degenerate expression of the spectacle-mediated, consumer-driven institution of contemporary charity. I would suggest that not only does today's 'spectacle charity' serve as the eternal plaster over a gaping, festering social wound, it actually functions directly to sustain the system that injures us. First, spectacle charity does this by alleviating social pressure. Legitimate frustration and anger at blatant social injustice is channeled 'productively' into charitable activity. Second, spectacle charity serves to appease feelings of guilt among those who are, or at least feel, better off and luckier. It also tells those unlucky ones they should be grateful they're not far worse off in some Third World urban slum. Third, spectacle charity reinforces capitalist social relations by asking us to help alleviate suffering by acting as consumers – buying cakes, red noses, corporate sponsors' products. Fourth, spectacle charity serves to maintain the status quo by providing depoliticised depictions of human suffering. The political-economic root causes of, say, child poverty in the UK are not and cannot be confronted. Poverty is portrayed in technical terms as a mere lack of things: money, education, resources. Fifth, in this way, spectacle charity reinforces the status quo by reinforcing general thoughtlessness. 'Don't think, do!' is the general message here. In all these ways Comic Relief, and charity in general, does more harm than good by serving to maintain the status quo economically, socially, and culturally. I shall offer some evidence for these claims. Yesterday, I tried to find out where Comic Relief's red noses were manufactured and what they were made from. Unfortunately, I was able to find out very little. With regard to labour, all I could establish was that Comic Relief had signed up, alongside other major charities and companies, to the 'Ethical Trading Initiative' (ETI) under which partner NGOs (non-government organisations) monitors the companies (presumably, predominantly in China) that manufacture their orders. I also found a mixed (albeit quite old) report on the ETI's effects by Sussex University, found out that several major companies, including Boots, had subsequently left the ETI, and that Primark, the company whose Bangladeshi subcontractors were guilty of the Rana Plaza tragedy in which 1,129 people needlessly died, is an ETI member. With regard to the environment, I could find nothing except for the fact that red noses can be recycled at various outlets. Whether the conditions in these factories had improved under ETI or not is, for me, secondary to the telling fact that I was not able to establish where Comic Relief's red noses were made. This tells us everything we need to know about the hidden, alienated nature of capitalist social relations and the institutions of commodified, spectacle charity within it. Comic Relief, an organisation dedicated to alleviating poverty, is largely blind to and reliant on the structure of class exploitation that creates this poverty. Thus, even if conditions are somewhat better in red nose factories, they are still exploitative. Why? Because it is the human labour within these factories that generates the surplus value that allows Comic Relief to sell these things for a profit. If this was not the case, these red noses would simply be produced in the UK. In terms of the environment, I am none the wiser, but pessimistic, as to the ecological cost of mass-producing millions of plastic red noses. Over a century ago, Oscar Wilde was acutely aware of the perversity of charity: 'It is immoral to use private property in order to alleviate the horrible evils that result from the institution of private property.' His ultimate conclusion resounds to this day: 'The proper aim is to try and reconstruct society on such a basis that poverty will be impossible.' The only thing that gives me heart on days like Red Nose Day is that people undoubtedly care. But, no amount of silly tomfoolery or hard, cold cash will end poverty. Capitalism breeds it, capitalism needs it. The goal of socialists like me is to encourage well-meaning, big-hearted folk (i.e. most people) to go beyond doing and take some time to explore and think about the root causes of our bleak situation. Ten years ago, the major charities in the UK came together under the banner of 'Make Poverty History'. Remember the white plastic wristbands? In the UK and beyond, poverty has increased in the past ten years.1 Let us, instead, take an approach that is at once more radical and realistic. To make poverty history means to make charity history, and to make charity history we must make capitalism history. If we don't, Oscar Wilde's words will continue to resonate yet another century from now.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How should cities deal with legacies of guilt?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/10/18/How-should-cities-deal-with-legacies-of-guilt.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How should cities deal with legacies of guilt?" /><published>2017-10-18T12:36:18+01:00</published><updated>2017-10-18T12:36:18+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/10/18/How-should-cities-deal-with-legacies-of-guilt</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2017/10/18/How-should-cities-deal-with-legacies-of-guilt.html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote this back in 2017…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;Dear reader,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;I haven't been blogging in recent months. I don't feel I have much to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;I have now moved to Bristol and I and my family are gradually settling in. The legacy of slavery looms large here and has loomed larger in recent years. The controversy of street and building names and, of course, monuments to slave-owners - most notably to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Colston&quot;&gt;Edward Colston&lt;/a&gt; - has arisen here, not with the overt violence seen in the US, but still with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.independent.co.uk/student/news/rhodes-must-fall-bristol-university-students-tower-henry-overton-wills-memorial-slave-trade-links-a7655721.html&quot;&gt;anger, passion, and division&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;  wp-image-6908 aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/statue-of-edward-colston.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;statue-of-edward-colston&quot; width=&quot;313&quot; height=&quot;559&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;This morning, I attended an event entitled '&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.watershed.co.uk/whatson/8438/how-should-cities-deal-with-the-legacies-of&quot;&gt;How should cities deal with legacies of guilt&lt;/a&gt;? at the Watershed in Bristol. The event was of the Festival of the Future City itself presented by the Bristol Festival of Ideas. It was hosted by historian &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2016/nov/04/david-olusoga-interview-black-history&quot;&gt;David Olusoga&lt;/a&gt; who facilitated a discussion between &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/timcole_bristol?lang=en&quot;&gt;Tim Cole&lt;/a&gt;, a historian of the politics of memory of the Holocaust; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MadgeDresser?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Eauthor&quot;&gt;Madge Dresser&lt;/a&gt;, a historian of Atlantic slavery and its effects on British culture; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Vanessa_Kisuule?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Eauthor&quot;&gt;Vanessa Kisuule&lt;/a&gt;, Bristol-based writer and performer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;Most of this hour-long discussion was a historically contextualised exploration of the politics and ethics of monuments. Central, understandably, was the question of whether monuments commemorating figures or regimes of violence should be brought down and, if so, what they should be replaced with. I was pleased to hear all three panelists speak supportively for monuments or artistic interventions that &lt;em&gt;open &lt;/em&gt;up space for public contribution. I too believe that any replacements, even when expressing desires or demands for justice, cannot be &lt;em&gt;monological &lt;/em&gt;entities that closed down space, but must be open and &lt;em&gt;dialogical&lt;/em&gt; inviting us all to contribute to the narratives, past, present, and future, that we as citizens, as common humanity, share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;At their best, however, such monuments or artistic interventions can only create &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/uk/dissensus-9781441119414/&quot;&gt;dissensus&lt;/a&gt; and spaces for transformation. They cannot be transformative in themselves. What must come next, then, have to be concrete processes that enable us all to work together towards truth, justice, and healing. It was disappointing for me, then, that, only when it was opened up for audience questions, did the discussion shift away from 'ideas' towards the realms of feelings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;The first contribution from the audience came from a young black woman who was clearly in a huge amount of pain. &lt;em&gt;As I interpreted it&lt;/em&gt;, she expressed feelings of 'humiliation' in living in Bristol and facing not just the continuing architecture of historical violence, but the continued racism of our city and society. Responding to her, Vanessa Kisuule acknowledge this woman's &lt;em&gt;feelings&lt;/em&gt;. Kisuule gestured to her, by touching her hand to her heart and chest, telling her 'I know!' These were the two most profound and important words of the whole event. I was saddened, therefore, that, perhaps just instinctively, David Olusoga, the chair, responded himself by reaching out, touching Kisuule's hand, and, jokingly, said something like 'Careful! This could go deep!' To be clear, this is not a &lt;em&gt;judgment &lt;/em&gt;of Olusoga's acts. I could well have possibly done the same thing. It felt like an articulation of an instinctive performance of regulating what can and can't be said at events like these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;Perhaps this wasn't the time and place for us to go deep; perhaps it was precisely the place. At some time, in some shared place, we &lt;em&gt;have to &lt;/em&gt;go deep. We have to go far, far beyond ideas if we seriously want to deal with legacies of guilt. Yes, guilt can be defined merely in technical legal terms or, more ethically, in historical evaluations, but guilt is, first and foremost, a &lt;em&gt;feeling&lt;/em&gt;. Where there are feelings of guilt, there is shame, there is violence, there is humiliation, there is vengeful anger, there is deep pain, there is trauma. Whether we like it or not, these are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kosmosjournal.org/article/thomas-hubls-the-pocket-project-facilitating-the-integration-of-collective-trauma/&quot;&gt;'deep lakes' of trauma&lt;/a&gt;, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.innerscience.info/en/thomas-huebl.html&quot;&gt;Thomas Hubl &lt;/a&gt;calls them - personal and collective - that sit in our subterranea. The closer we are, historically and culturally, to their source, the more physically and spiritually we feel them, true. But, since we are one, we all feel them. There are hegemonic constructions not just of ideas but of feelings that lay the foundations and scaffolding for what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloria_E._Anzald%C3%BAa&quot;&gt;Gloria Anzaldua&lt;/a&gt; has called our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dukeupress.edu/light-in-the-dark-luz-en-lo-oscuro&quot;&gt;'desconocimientos'&lt;/a&gt; - ‘The ignorance we cultivate to keep ourselves from knowledge so that we can remain unaccountable'. But, however, sturdy these constructions, those deep, wide lakes remain below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;A quick example of feelings. After the event, I spoke briefly with Vanessa Kisuule. What words were said are of secondary importance. Let me faithfully share my feelings. I felt like a white man telling a black woman about racism and injustice. I felt awkward. I felt like I was patronising even though I had no such intention. I felt like I wanted to be an equal human being with her, but I felt divided. I did not feel guilt. Please try not to judge these emotions. I've had a black woman tell me before that I should get over myself. She might be right. However, these feelings are not, as I understand them, feelings of self-pity at all. They are feelings of alienation from another human being with whom and for whom I want equality, justice, and solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;I went home from the Watershed, cycling up those bastard Bristol hills in the drizzle. I got home, got my wet clothes off, changed into dry clothes, and sat down. I became aware of huge, powerful forces of feeling inside me - in my chest, my stomach, my throat. I decided to take 10 minutes to feel them. I sank down into them and images soon came to me. I was working some land by the side of a cliff which descended down into the sea. The grass was bright green, the sea bright blue, the cliff bright white. Suddenly, I was struck and cut on my shoulder. I saw a small beaten boy. He was dead. His body was pushed off the cliff. It bounced with thuds down to the sea below. Next, I was a man whipping the bloody, serrated back of a woman. Then, I was swimming in the sea through bodies and debris, fires from the cliffs. Was it a revolt? I don't know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;Wounds can be bridges, declares Gloria Anzaldua. We fragment, we can reunite. But, these bridges are conscious processes of healing that we as a society need to build. I am currently involved in a process of group work, inspired and organised by Thomas Hubl, that seeks to delve deep into our personal and collective lakes of trauma in preparation for its participants to facilitate and support other processes of healing. But, what I am acutely conscious of in this and all processes is the need for those most direct victims of violence - not just the gratuitously physical, but the humiliating, dehumanising cultural, symbolic, often unwitting, everyday violence - to be silent no more and to name that violence, their feelings. In such processes, not only do they pronounce their own humanity (always there, but denied by the system), but they shine a light out of the dark towards our own reclaimed, unified, more complete humanity. This, I believe, nay, I &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt;, is how we must and &lt;em&gt;can &lt;/em&gt;go forward in order for us all not just 'deal with', but to &lt;em&gt;overcome &lt;/em&gt;legacies of guilt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;Thank you for reading&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;Blessings and peace to you&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:justify;&quot;&gt;Joel&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joel Lazarus</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">I wrote this back in 2017… Dear reader, I haven't been blogging in recent months. I don't feel I have much to say. I have now moved to Bristol and I and my family are gradually settling in. The legacy of slavery looms large here and has loomed larger in recent years. The controversy of street and building names and, of course, monuments to slave-owners - most notably to Edward Colston - has arisen here, not with the overt violence seen in the US, but still with anger, passion, and division.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The most important thing I’ve probably ever written in my life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2016/02/16/the-most-important-thing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The most important thing I’ve probably ever written in my life" /><published>2016-02-16T11:36:18+00:00</published><updated>2016-02-16T11:36:18+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2016/02/16/the-most-important-thing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2016/02/16/the-most-important-thing.html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote this back in 2016…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FROM &lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;DEATH&lt;/span&gt; TO &lt;span style=&quot;color:#008000;&quot;&gt;LIFE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;M-C-M'/C-M-C&lt;/span&gt; → &lt;span style=&quot;color:#339966;&quot;&gt;U-I-U'/I-U-I'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;I am currently organising an 'unconference'. I'm inviting a diverse group of around 30 people to a weekend workshop in April focused on the issue of transformation. That's intentionally left very broad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;One of the people I have invited, a gent by the name of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/matthewpainton&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew Painton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, has so kindly offered to give me the gift of five free hours of his time. Matthew is a 'life coach'. This title has perhaps cheesy connotations, but there is nothing cheesy about what Matthew has done for me. There are no words to express my gratitude to him...And we're only two hours in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;What I'm asking you to read for me below, dearest reader, is probably the most important thing I've ever written in my life. I wrote this immediately after the experience I describe in the writing. This experience came soon after Matthew and I had completed our second session. The experience I describe took place about 10 hours ago. It's now 21:10 and I've tidied what I wrote up a bit, added a few explanatory sentences, but intentionally left it as raw as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If what you read here resonates with you, if it moves you then please do let me know. You can leave a comment or you can email me at joel underscore lazarus at hotmail dot com. I would love to hear from you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;With thanks and with love&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;Joel...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M-C-M' (M = Money; C = Commodity; M' = More Money)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This equation – the equation that reveals the alchemic secret of money – comes from &lt;i&gt;Capital, Vol I&lt;/i&gt; by Karl Marx. What it shows is that, in our world, money isn't the object we think it is. Money is the &lt;i&gt;subject&lt;/i&gt;. Money capital uses us! It uses us to grow, to incessantly grow.&lt;/strong&gt; We are the objects it uses for self-valorisation. Hence vampire and zombie analogies in &lt;i&gt;Capital&lt;/i&gt; and many popular cultures. Capital is vampire; we are zombies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;But if we accept this real abstraction as the total force forming the organising principle of our world, the subject controlling our lives, we must also be open to the possibility that &lt;strong&gt;we are or could be the objects of an &lt;i&gt;alternative &lt;/i&gt;subject. Something else could drive our lives instead of money capital.
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today, with the help of Matthew Painton, I found that subject – it is the universe, the totality of life itself. It is inside me. It is inside you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;We cannot possibly feel it constantly. How could we function in our daily lives? We need, to an extent, to suppress it and, in the process, we anaesthetise ourselves. But the totality and incessant pressure that money puts on us inevitably makes us unconsciously and almost permanently repress &lt;i&gt;this &lt;/i&gt;subject in favour of serving money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;But what we suppress or repress doesn't go away. It is there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What motivates us to stand up for, to even give our lives, for others – for family, for friends, for community, society, for a forest, for a mountain, for Nature? First and foremost, it's not an argument, it's not an idea, an ideology; it's a feeling.&lt;/strong&gt; We feel the injustice, the pain, the suffering. Only then comes the intellectual rationalisation. And that's crucial, but that rationalisation does also function to limit the feeling, the raw emotion. So...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:underline;color:#008000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What if we turn off the mind for a bit and just let the feelings flow?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#339966;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can one possibly even begin to feel the totality of pain and suffering in the world? I don't know. But today I tried to do just this...&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I sat still, closed my eyes and tried to feel the pain and suffering in the world. I felt the searing, shattering pain of a parent's grief; I felt the physical and spiritual agony of a human being violated, of another imprisoned, another tortured; I felt the stabbing hunger of a starving belly. I felt the humiliation of a Muslim woman vilified, a disabled person taunted; a young black man demonised.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I felt the numbing silent devastation of a forest burned, a river poisoned, a sacred mountain decapitated.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is a unity to every living thing on this planet. There is a unity to body and mind. Until today, I couldn't see the unity that connected Marx's revolutionary science of historical materialism to a spirituality that emphasises above all the interconnectedness of all things, of materiality and consciousness. Today I see it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In our society, it is money capital that is the organising principle, the totality, the subject, the absolute Emperor of our society. Marx's revolutionary formula reveals this: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;M-C-M'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;Money feeds on our bodies and minds to grow.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I&lt;strong&gt;n this Emperor's world, we are objects. We are C-M-C. We sell our bodies and minds, our labour-power, for money in order to use this money to sustain our existences and consume the energy needed to reproduce ourselves once again for money.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;The money world, the society of capitalism, is ecocidal and it is genocidal. This is the death equation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#008000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But, there is another revolutionary equation – the equation for our time, the equation that tells us the true source of life, the life equation. It is, I think, this…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#008000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;U-I-U' and I-U-I'&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#008000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In this pair of equations, U stands for the universe or universal life. I is I, myself. This is the life equation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the first pair, the death pair (M-C-M'/C-M-C), money flourishes at our expense – a zero-sum situation. In the second pair, the life equation, life itself and I, as both independent subject in and object for life, flourish. A positive-sum situation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rather than money, the totalising subject here, the Emperor, is the universe, universal life, the totality of all living beings. Universal life is expressed and embodied in specific living beings (I) and through us all it seeks to flourish and grow. In contrast to living in order to serve the money emperor of death, &lt;span style=&quot;color:#008000;&quot;&gt;if I seeks to live its life guided by and in harmony with the infinite power of U, I itself flourishes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#008000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:underline;&quot;&gt;U is life. U is truth. U is beauty. U is love. For some, U is God.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;This is an intellectualisation of U and we do need to think about U and how we live practically, how we organise our society, in a flourishing relationship with U, but U is not primarily an idea. &lt;strong&gt;U is not an ideology. U is a power, a power that is felt.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:underline;color:#008000;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today I felt U. I sat, closed my eyes and flowed...&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#008000;&quot;&gt;I was the whale deep down in the dark blue sea. I was a blind pelican being fed fish by other fellow pelicans, the sun on my face, a writhing fish in my mouth. I was a murmuration of starlings, thick, pulsating. I was a bison. I was a herd of bison. I was a penguin sheltering with others from a blizzard. I was a hare running. I was a chimpanzee perched in a tree, eating fruit. I was even a spider creeping forward slowly. I was a child running towards the sun...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:underline;color:#008000;&quot;&gt;Do this for me, for yourself, for universal life today. Take 10mins that you think you desperately need in your work (to serve M). Sit down, close your eyes, breathe with all your belly, deep breaths, and explore what you feel. What do you feel? Feel the feeling, be in the feeling, and let it take you on a journey.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:underline;color:#008000;&quot;&gt; I'd be honoured to hear from you what you felt and where you went. This is inside all of us, all the time – a feeling of infinite power and goodness there to guide us.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt; The goal is to destroy the deathworld of money, yes, but through empowering the world of life that money is sucking dry. The feeling will guide us. Through it, and only through it, we see that what we &lt;i&gt;think&lt;/i&gt; is impossible, we &lt;i&gt;feel&lt;/i&gt; and know to be possible and the only real way - the loving way.
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:underline;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#339966;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt; To the flourishing of all life!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joel Lazarus</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">I wrote this back in 2016…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What does the ‘economy’ look like and why does it matter?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2016/02/11/what-does-economy-look-like.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What does the ‘economy’ look like and why does it matter?" /><published>2016-02-11T11:36:18+00:00</published><updated>2016-02-11T11:36:18+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2016/02/11/what-does-economy-look-like</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2016/02/11/what-does-economy-look-like.html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a two-part blog…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Question: ‘What does the economy &lt;i&gt;look &lt;/i&gt;like?…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;The mainstream economist's answer: 'Why! GDP, of course!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;'An economy,' a mainstream economist might retort, 'is nothing more than the combined economic activity of all 'households' in any given location – say, a region, a nation, the world. So, if you want to see what an economy looks like, consult the charts that portray these aggregated numbers'. &lt;strong&gt;The specific chart that visually depicts our national economy is, of course, that portraying 'GDP' (Gross Domestic Product).&lt;a class=&quot;sdfootnoteanc&quot; href=&quot;#sdfootnote1sym&quot; name=&quot;sdfootnote1anc&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot; size-full wp-image-4130 aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/01/gdp-ons.png&quot; alt=&quot;GDP ONS&quot; width=&quot;620&quot; height=&quot;349&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;To be fair to mainstream economists, the GDP figure and chart does spur subsequent investigations into, and depictions of, other, subsidiary sectors: trade, manufacturing, consumption, employment, etc. But, &lt;strong&gt;it remains the case that were one to ask most economists what the economy looks like they'd probably show you the GDP chart.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;The supply-demand curve&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;The historical GDP chart tracks our interminable quest for that holy grail - economic growth. &lt;strong&gt;If economic growth is the proclaimed overarching objective of our society then the path to this objective lies through the venerated 'market'. Aesthetically, the sanctity of the market is revealed to us in the 'supply-demand curve'.&lt;/strong&gt; This simple two line chart shows us how the Lord weaves his miracles daily, bringing forth social order and justice from atomised chaos with each wave of his 'invisible hand'. For atheist free-marketeers, God is the market itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot; size-full wp-image-4135 aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/01/demandsupplycurve.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demandsupplycurve&quot; width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;349&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This sanctification of the market serves as a foundational myth of our economic religion – established in the 'scriptures' of founding texts, peddled by the priesthood, and reinforced and institutionalised in schools, universities, TV programmes and films every day of our lives.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;The minimalist aesthetic of hegemonic microeconomics&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;This is not a blogpost debunking the preposterous myth of the free market. It is a post focused on how our economy is portrayed aesthetically. From this perspective, then, I think it is safe to share Susan Buck-Morss' conclusion that that &lt;strong&gt;the hegemonic economics of today, neoclassical economics, is 'microeconomics'…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;padding-left:30px;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;'Minimalism is characteristic of the supply-demand curve, none of the substantive problems of political economy are resolved, while the social whole simply disappears from sight. Once this happens, critical reflection on the exogenous conditions of a 'given' market situation becomes impossible, and the philosophy of political economy become so theoretically impoverished that it can be said to come to an end.'&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;What does this all mean? As I understand it, &lt;strong&gt;a central political function of neoclassical economics is to depoliticise our society. By using their technical equations and graphs to depict the economy, economists perplex us into accepting that the status quo is the natural and only possible social order. They also point our attention to exchange and consumption away from the politics of production and work. Neoclassical economists, the aspiring physicists of the social sciences, using their 'scientific expertise' to close down political possibilities&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;a class=&quot;sdfootnoteanc&quot; href=&quot;#sdfootnote2sym&quot; name=&quot;sdfootnote2anc&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Only by reducing the complexity of individual and social life to this degree can one create an aesthetic as minimalist as the GDP or supply-demand curve chart to represent the 'economy' – an entity that structures, and is structured by, millions, indeed billions, of human beings.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;This is not to dismiss the usefulness of using graphs and charts to reveal important economic trends and factors. It is, instead, to argue that &lt;strong&gt;when economists reduce the aesthetic portrayal of the economy to such graphs they render invisible the social and close the politically possible, making those exploited within the current economic system invisible and silent.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Seeing the unseeable&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;Visibility and invisibility are at the very heart of the issue here, for repoliticising our economy means attempting to somehow show that it comprises billions of unique human lives connected and structured through social relations of power. Above all, &lt;strong&gt;a &lt;i&gt;political &lt;/i&gt;economic attempt to answer the question of what the economy looks like must try to show that what is invisible when we try to &lt;i&gt;see &lt;/i&gt;the economy is just as real as the visible, if not more so.&lt;/strong&gt; This, on first consideration, shouldn't be that hard. We all believe in the existence of things we can't see: electricity, gravity, microorganisms even. But, the complexity and dynamism of social systems and structures mean that their existence can't be scientifically seen or aesthetically represented in similar ways. They are, as Karl Marx put it, 'real abstractions'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;  wp-image-4144 aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/01/turkish-food-porn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;turkish food porn.png&quot; width=&quot;614&quot; height=&quot;409&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gratuitous T&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;urki&lt;/em&gt;sh food porn!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take a look at your next plate of food. Now try to think of all the human beings, animals, and natural contributions involved in ensuring its presence on your table. When you really start to work it through, you soon realise that we're talking about countless combinations of literally millions of human beings and living creatures. Just because we have not met them does it mean we have no relation to and with them? Their labour, their very lives, have played a vital role in sustaining our own. There can be no more materially real relation than this, yet, no visible trace of this collective labour, energy, life can be seen on our plates. An understandable response to this is to feign blindness. But, if we remain blind to our place within the complex social system that we call our economy how can we see beyond the end of our own forks? How can we how to change our economy, our society, for the better if we can't or won't see it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;'Cartographies of the Absolute'!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;This is the dilemma admirably addressed by Alberto Toscano and Jeff Kinkel in their recent book &lt;i&gt;Cartographies of the Absolute&lt;/i&gt;. When one gets past the intellectually terrifying title, one finds, in many places, some no less terrifying prose. Yet, Toscano and Kinkel's contribution to our question is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot; size-full wp-image-4149 aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/01/1439234375_cartographies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1439234375_Cartographies&quot; width=&quot;549&quot; height=&quot;527&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This graphic was produced by William Bunge as appears on the front cover of Toscano &amp;amp; Kinkle's book &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;'Cartographies of the Absolute'&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;Writing in the Marxist tradition, and taking us on a wonderful tour of contemporary art and film, the 'absolute' that the authors confront is none other than capital itself – the entity, the force that binds us all in relations of coercion, exploitation, and alienation each day, each very minute. Capital is everywhere, pulsing ceaselessly through our transplanetary and biological veins, making our very world go round, making and remaking our very selves. Capital produces us and we produce capital. And, as Toscano and Kinkel rightly emphasise, since capitalism is full of antagonisms and contradictions, we are too. &lt;strong&gt;Capital is, then, for the vast majority of humanity, the 'absolute' force shaping our lives and fates. And, yet, its very absoluteness, its ubiquity, makes it unseen, 'hidden in plain view'. This is why we can't realistically hope to see 'the economy' - the economy is the totality of global class relations within which we ourselves are immersed.&lt;/strong&gt; Ultimately, as Frederic Jameson puts it, any attempts at mapping the whole economy 'disorient under the banner of orientation'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;The view from below&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;There is no need, however, as Toscano and Kinkel themselves emphasise, to let this conclusion paralyse us intellectually or politically. Though we must discard any efforts to map this absolute, we still need some kind of cognitive mapping to inform our political understanding and our strategic actions. Frederic Jameson contends that 'the view from the top is epistemologically crippling'.&lt;a class=&quot;sdfootnoteanc&quot; href=&quot;#sdfootnote3sym&quot; name=&quot;sdfootnote3anc&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let's proceed instead then from the bottom. If the dominant way that our economy is aesthetically depicted serves to render silent and invisible its greatest victims then let us listen to those rendered silent and let us find out what economy they can see.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, what does the economy look like from below? Here's one view. Dear readers, I proudly present what I call the 'Flo Chart'!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;  wp-image-4157 aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/01/the-flo-chart.jpg?w=680&quot; alt=&quot;The Flo Chart&quot; width=&quot;455&quot; height=&quot;609&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 'Flo Chart'!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;This picture was drawn by me, but it's reproduced from memory of the original which was drawn by a wonderful woman called Flo during the first PPE (People's Political Economy) learning group I ran at The Hub, a community centre in Hodge Hill, Birmingham back in the Autumn of last year. &lt;strong&gt;I asked the group to express in any way they wanted what they thought and felt when they heard the word 'economy'. This is the picture that Flo produced in response to that question. Flo is an older woman who, by her own admission, has no formal understanding of economics or what an economy is. Listening to her tell us all, quite openly, the extreme challenges that life has thrown at her, it was clear where Flo saw herself and others at The Hub within her Flo Chart: very much at the bottom.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It's an amazing picture to analyse. What I see I'm tempted to call 'the absolute'. I see everything, everyone contained within this balloon (this bubble?). I see a few on top and others falling down to join 'the masses' at the bottom. I see the huddled folk at the bottom keeping the air in the whole thing by plugging up the balloon. The Flo Chart shows our ultimate interdependence – those on the top need those on the bottom. They would quickly fall to Earth if those below were to unplug the balloon.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clearly, the Flo Chart makes no scientific representation. No data is being displayed here. But, if the GDP chart shows us an economy then the Flo Chart shows us the politics of, the unequal social relations structuring, that economy. Moreover, the Flo Chart shows us the artistry, the eloquence, the intellectual and creative power (and potential) of the dispossessed. The view from below isn't just indispensable for getting a better view of (understanding) our economy, our society, it's indispensable because the process by which people at the bottom of our economy, our society are invited to share their vision is, when it's done right, a process of intellectual and, ultimately, political empowerment. In short, working with people at the bottom is central to building our democracy and democratising our economy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Re-envisioning our economy&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People are intelligent, insightful, and creative. Without knowledge of social theory, they might not always have the words or concepts to articulate their intelligence, but, still, their intelligence and creativity comes out, often with devastating power. The task of folk like me (I'm falling slowly in the middle), with knowledge of social theory, is to help people at the bottom to cultivate their own intelligence to see further. The word 'theory' comes from the Greek 'theories' meaning 'to see', 'to behold'. When we combine the social knowledge that everyone has with the scientific knowledge that some are privileged to have then we can produce the transformational knowledge we need to reimagine and recreate our world.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The question of what our economy looks like is of fundamental, of foundational, importance. It's the firm basis on which we can rebuild. Seeing our economy to the best of our abilities requires looking from multiple vantage points not least from below. We need to create a vision (or visions) of our economy that combine our shared experiential with our scientific/theoretical knowledge and, indeed, our emotions. It's important because only from this foundation can we start to re-envision – to reimage and recreate an economy within our society – in a truly democratic fashion.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;second part of this blog&lt;/a&gt;, I will offer some ideas, drawn from my own praxis of community education and theoretical work, for how we can generate collective visions of our economy as foundations for re-envisioning ourselves and our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;sdfootnote1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;sdfootnotesym&quot; href=&quot;#sdfootnote1anc&quot; name=&quot;sdfootnote1sym&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;The Gross Domestic Product figure measures the total monetary value of all goods and services produced in an economy over a given period of time. It is usually expressed as a percentage rise or fall compared to the previous year or quarter.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;sdfootnote2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;sdfootnotesym&quot; href=&quot;#sdfootnote2anc&quot; name=&quot;sdfootnote2sym&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt;Although we see the establishment of a separate realm of human activity in classical economists like Adam Smith and David Ricardo, Smith and Ricardo were still very much interested in understanding where economic &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;value&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt; came from and, while they reduced social and political relationships to the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt;bourgeois technical&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt; language&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt;of inputs/outputs, investments, profits, and returns, they did at least recognise that value was created by human labour. It was the 'Marginalist Revolution' of the final third of the 19&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt;th&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt; Century, lead by William Stanley Jevons in England, Carl Menger in Austria, and Leon Walras in Switzerland, that sought to bury any notion of the origin of value as somehow social and political, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt;dethroning classical political economy with&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt; the theory of marginal utility. Instead of any consideration of social theory and value, economics became, and remains to this day, a consideration of utility and prices. The only social theory &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt;here&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt; is really that 'man' is out to satisfy his desires and minimise his work. This quest for 'marginal' utility (and avoidance of marginal disutility) – how much he will give for any additional unit of something he desires - combines with the positioning of the market as optimal mechanism for blindly, but efficiently, allocating scarce resources in the economy to form the cornerstones of the neoclassical economic religion.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;sdfootnote3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:small;&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;sdfootnotesym&quot; href=&quot;#sdfootnote3anc&quot; name=&quot;sdfootnote3sym&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;I understand this to mean that, rather than enhancing our understanding of our common humanity, our ability to see our planet the Earth from above, for example, has, conversely, increased our sense of bewilderment and powerlessness.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Joel Lazarus</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">This is the first of a two-part blog…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What does the ‘economy’ look like? Part Two: developing the view from below</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2015/01/09/what-does-economy-look-like-pt2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What does the ‘economy’ look like? Part Two: developing the view from below" /><published>2015-01-09T11:36:18+00:00</published><updated>2015-01-09T11:36:18+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2015/01/09/what-does-economy-look-like-pt2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2015/01/09/what-does-economy-look-like-pt2.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;A brief summary of Part One of this post&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/jekyll/update/2016/02/11/what-does-economy-look-like.html&quot;&gt;In an earlier blogpost entitled ‘What does the economy look like? And why does it matter?’&lt;/a&gt;, I critiqued mainstream graphic representations of the economy, giving the examples of the commonly spotted GDP chart and supply-demand curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot; size-full wp-image-4130 aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/01/gdp-ons.png&quot; alt=&quot;GDP ONS&quot; width=&quot;620&quot; height=&quot;349&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;  wp-image-4135 aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/01/demandsupplycurve.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demandsupplycurve&quot; width=&quot;478&quot; height=&quot;397&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;Without dismissing the usefulness of graphs and charts to reveal important economic trends and factors, I argued that 'when economists reduce the aesthetic portrayal of the economy to such graphs they render invisible the social and close the politically possible, making those exploited within the current economic system invisible and silent'. In short, &lt;strong&gt;economics depoliticises by hiding the deeper reality which is that the economy is ultimately made up of social and natural &lt;i&gt;relations&lt;/i&gt;, that is&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;relations between ourselves and nature&lt;/strong&gt;. I gave the example of something as everyday and essential as a plate of food and asked readers to think about all the human and non-human life that contributed to producing and delivering this food. It is almost impossible to account for all contributing lives here. Yet, they are real and we are bound with them in global systems of relations of production, exchange, and consumption. &lt;strong&gt;There can be no more materially real relations to us than the ones between the lives that make our life possible and yet these people, these natural elements are invisible to us. If we wish to change our economy, we need to somehow &lt;i&gt;see&lt;/i&gt; our economy, and this means making the invisible somehow visible. We need to see, to some degree at least, the social systems structuring our economy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;I then introduced a recent book by Alberto Toscano and Jeff Kinkel called &lt;i&gt;Cartographies of the Absolute&lt;/i&gt;. Don't let the title frighten you! It's a good one actually because it refers succinctly and directly to the central issue. How can we make visible something that is both at the same time everywhere and seemingly nowhere? How can we render static that which is constantly moving and changing? Toscano and Kinkel are interested here in the absolute that is capital, that&lt;strong&gt; ‘absolute’ force shaping our lives and fates. And, yet, its very absoluteness, its ubiquity, makes it unseen, ‘hidden in plain view’. This is why we can’t realistically hope to see ‘the economy’ – the economy is the totality of global class relations within which we ourselves are immersed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot; size-full wp-image-4149 aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/01/1439234375_cartographies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1439234375_Cartographies&quot; width=&quot;549&quot; height=&quot;527&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimately, as Frederic Jameson puts it, any attempts at mapping the whole economy ‘disorient under the banner of orientation’. But, as Toscano and Kinkel rightly emphasise, this mustn't paralyse us. Though we must discard any efforts to map this absolute, we still need some kind of cognitive mapping to inform our political understanding and our strategic actions. If, as Frederic Jameson contends, ‘the view from the top is epistemologically crippling’, why not start from the bottom instead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;In the final section of Part One, I proposed that if the dominant way that our economy is aesthetically depicted serves to render silent and invisible its greatest victims then let us listen to those rendered silent and let us find out what economy they can see. I then introduced what I call the 'Flo Chart', a pictorial representation of the economy produced by a wonderful woman called Flo who participated in a learning group I ran in Hodge Hill, Birmingham. Here's the picture of the Flo Chart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;  wp-image-4157 aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/01/the-flo-chart.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Flo Chart&quot; width=&quot;422&quot; height=&quot;565&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Flo Chart shows us that, &lt;strong&gt;even without the technical language, people can demonstrate remarkable insight and have much to teach others about our world. In this case, what Flo captures, beyond the charts and graphs, are the social relations of the economy, the exploitative nature of those relations, and our ultimate interdependence.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;Finally, in Part One, I argued that, beyond merely recognising and including the knowledge and insight generated by people at the bottom of our society, the view from below isn’t just indispensable for getting a better view of (understanding) our economy, our society, it’s indispensable because the process by which people at the bottom of our economy, our society are invited to share their vision is, when it’s done right, a process of intellectual and, ultimately, political empowerment. In short, working with people at the bottom is central and vital to building our democracy and democratising our economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Seeing the Economy, Part Two: Learning inspired&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;In Part Two of this blogpost here, I offer some ideas, drawn from my own praxis of community education and theoretical work, for how we can generate collective visions of our economy as foundations for re-envisioning ourselves and our society. I focus on role-playing exercises that I have conducted with two groups of people in recent months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;The role play&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;Ken Loach is a now legendary film director who has spent six decades making beautiful and brave social realist films. He has allowed us to see them all &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/KenLoachFilms&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. His films have directly influenced society and politics in this country and beyond. I haven't seen Ken Loach's latest film &lt;i&gt;I, Daniel Blake &lt;/i&gt;yet. The film recently won the 'Palme d'Or' award for the best film at the Cannes Film Festival. What I have seen, however, is a two-minute clip from the film which you can see here.
&amp;lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/J3E5__ga96g&quot; &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When I saw this clip I was immediately struck by how similar it was to the role play scenarios devised and performed by the participants in the learning groups I facilitate. In two separate learning groups, I have worked with participants to devise role plays set in benefits offices/job centres like this one. Our sessions go from sharing our stories, performing a role play, discussing the experience of the role play, and then, finally, analysing the role play politically.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sharing our stories and performing the role play&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The sessions begin with each other sharing their stories.&lt;/strong&gt; I then invite participants to use their own experiences and stories to imagine the setting of the benefits office or job centre, to take roles within the office, and to perform these roles. I then allow the participants themselves to develop the scenario. My job is only to ask them occasionally if they think that what they are performing feels realistic, authentic to them. I loosely use the techniques of '&lt;a href=&quot;http://dramaresource.com/forum-theatre/&quot;&gt;Forum Theatre&lt;/a&gt;' developed by Brazilian dramatist and educator Augusto Boal. Hence, I invite other participants watching to take the place of the current actors in order to try to develop, or ideally resolve, the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;In one group, a young father whose benefits have been frozen for missing an appointment tells a benefits officer that the reason he missed his appointment was because his son had broken his arm and he had to take him to the hospital. The benefits officer, in a similarly officious and detached manner to that displayed in the film clip, informs the young man that he should have written a letter to that effect and will now have to reapply. The young man protests, saying that he is here in person now, that he has no money at all and two hungry kids at home. He appeals for understanding, for empathy, and for support. He is told that he can apply for a hardship fund, but that this application would still take two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;In another group, the scenario is of a young man with learning disabilities who needs to be accepted for a particular disability benefit in order to qualify for assisted housing. When his case is rejected, he meets a similar bureaucratic wall. In this group's case, it ended up with an emotional and irate applicant being physically removed from the building by the security guard just like the scenario in &lt;i&gt;I, Daniel Blake&lt;/i&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The final step in our process was to ask participants, still in their roles, about their lives and their position in the scenario. We then ended our role plays and discussed what had happened in them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;The discussion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We focus very much on feelings in our discussions. There are feelings of fear, anger, frustration, and powerlessness, of course, on the part of those playing the roles of the applicants.&lt;/strong&gt; I recall people saying how they just wanted to be understood, to be recognised, to be treated as a human being. For the applicants it is a very dehumanising experience. But, what of the benefits office staff? When I ask the people who played those roles, I get similar responses too. They speak of the stress, the pressure of their jobs; the long hours and low pay and the constant line of 'clients'; and how they feel they have to disconnect from the people they serve in order to protect their own sanity. This is a fascinating and important insight. It's easy enough to watch the film clip above all come away thinking that the benefits office staff are the bad guys, but are they? They too are suffering, they too are dehumanised. In a recent meeting with my friends at My Life My Choice where we watched and discussed this film clip, one participant did a quick internet search to find out what a security guard in the North East of England might earn. She found an advert for a security guard in Middlesborough with G4S offering £7.50 per hour! &lt;strong&gt;So, if not one of the people present in that situation is benefiting, who is? What is going on?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;The analysis&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From our discussion we then moved to analysis. We focused our analyses on the issue of power&lt;/strong&gt;. Who has the least, who has the most power here? In our MLMC meeting, we agreed that those with the least power – those most silenced, unable to speak and act, and most threatened by the material consequences of the situation – were the young woman's children. Then came the young woman herself, then the security guard, the benefits officer, and finally the manager. Yet, we also agreed that the manager himself had very little actual power and was just implementing rules and laws set from elsewhere. You can read a summary of this session &lt;a href=&quot;http://mylifemychoice.org.uk/power-in-the-job-centre/&quot;&gt;here on the MLMC website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, in all these sessions, we start following the power and that leads us upwards – to regional managers, yes, but then to the Department of Work and Pensions, the Minister in charge of the DWP, the government, the Prime Minister, the political parties, the Houses of Commons and Lords that make the laws and decide the budgets. But, then who are the people in these institutions? What backgrounds are they from? Are they rich or are they poor? Are they black, brown, or white? Are they male or female? Able-bodied or disabled? Do they know what life is like on the bottom or not? From where do they and their parties get their financial support? From the people or from the large corporations and banks? What about the media that is so important a political and cultural force? Who owns and populates the highest ranks of the media?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asking such questions leads us to draw 'maps' of power like this one from our recent MLMC session. Sorry this one's not a great example – it was hastily drawn and is incomplete, but it gives you enough to see where it can and does go.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot; size-full wp-image-4878 aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://agentofhistory.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/power-and-job-centre-diagram.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Power-and-job-centre-diagram&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;698&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We begin to draw a map of one small area of the capitalist system and we begin to see how it is linked to political power. But, we could go further and we must. We must also ask why. Why does this woman have to claim benefits? Why do we have a benefits system? Why are benefits being cut so savagely? This brings in economic power – austerity and its roots in the global financial crisis. We could go further and further, wider and wider, geographically, historically, socially. There is a limit and we cannot, as Toscano and Kinkel rightly say, actually map the absolute. But, just to make a start here is crucial. We can actually see how relations of power, very real and violent ones, are not always, indeed are rarely, between people in the same place at the same time. Power flows through us in systems of relations that connect billions of human beings over huge distances, but that doesn't make them any less real.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One final thing of the utmost importance to point out is the function of the security guard. The security guard's presence shows us that this is a system that is always ultimately underpinned and secured by physical violence.&lt;/strong&gt; The security guard represents violence and the violence is that of the nation-state. In turn, the nation-state is the embodiment of all social relations of domination that we experience. The person selling their labour-power as the security guard may have little power in their own lives, but as a security guard s/he embodies the violent power of the state. This is a painful schizophrenic life to lead for anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;The power of role play-led analysis&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;I find role plays really powerful, potentially transformative, exercises for several reasons. First, as I say, it helps us to see invisible but very real systems of relations of power and violence. Second, by using our bodies as well as our minds, we come to embody this new understanding in deeper, more sustainable ways. Third, and related, we learn with an energy and we work to produce &lt;em&gt;our own&lt;/em&gt; knowledge based on &lt;em&gt;our own&lt;/em&gt; experiences and insights. Fourth, by inhabiting the lives and roles of other people, even supposed enemies, we can develop our understanding, our empathy, our humanity. This is what makes such exercises and analyses potentially transformative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The big challenge, however, is the next step. Seeing the vastest of the system can be helpful and is necessary, but it can feel disempowering, of course, and we need to all feel empowered so that we can change things. I will write more about this in future blogs, but, for me, the general approach is three-fold: First, we can take things back to the level of our own lives, to our own local communities and ask ourselves what we can do for ourselves and each other right now; Second, we can explore the system more, see the contradictions within it that lead to crisis, see how historically contingent it is and that there was a world before it and will be a world after it; Third, this leads us to think in more utopian ways about the world we actually want. We have to develop a shared sense of what we want, both in the short-term and in the long-term. This is the work we all need to do.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;In Part One of this blogpost, I emphasised the importance of social theory – that even without knowledge of social theory, people's intelligence, insights, and creativity shine through, but that social theory can give us all a richer language to cultivate our own intelligence and understanding. It's the combination of experiential knowledge (that we all have) and scientific knowledge (that social theory can give us) that can produce transformational knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A central focus of developing this transformational knowledge that we need for our new lives and society must be on our economy. Here, the question of what our economy looks like is of fundamental, of foundational, importance. It’s the firm basis on which we can rebuild. Only from this foundation can we start to reimagine and recreate an economy within our society in a truly democratic fashion. Democratic work always starts from the bottom-up. It is challenging, but truly rewarding and socially necessary work and it brings me into wonderful relationships with amazing, intelligent, and creative people. I am very fortunate to be blessed in this way.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joel Lazarus</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>